Guide to the Francis Warrington Dawson Family Papers, 1386-1963, bulk 1859-1950 RL.10147
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1
  - Dawson Family Writings, 1
    - Dawson, Warrington. Vengeance Cast Away, undated (Box 53)
      Typescript. With foreword by Vance Thompson and preface by author.
    - Dawson, Warrington. Versailles S&O France, 1950 (Box 53)
      Typescript. Short entries dated Jan. 28 and March 3, 1950.
    - Dawson, Warrington. The Virgin of Ivory, 1923; 9 folders (Box 53-54)
      Manuscript. 3 bound volumes. Typescript of English original and French translation.
    - Dawson, Warrington. A Volunteer in Secret Service, undated (Box 54)
    - Dawson, Warrington. What Charleston Needs, undated (Box 54)
      Manuscript. Lecture.
    - Dawson, Warrington. William Graves Sharp, undated; 2 folders (Box 54)
      Typescript. Dawson's work on William Graves Sharp's memoirs. Translation rights and miscellaneous pieces and translations.
    - Dawson, Warrington. The Will of Tabitya Raddon: A Play in Three Acts, undated (Box 54)
    - Dawson, Warrington. With Roosevelt in Africa, 1909-1911; 3 folders (Box 54)
      Typescript accompanied by list of dates between 1909 and 1911 that lecture was given. 3 slightly different copies.
    - Dawson, Warrington. [World War I Memos], undated (Box 55)
    - Dawson, Warrington. [Writings Concerning the Death of F.W. Dawson, I], 1946, 1958, undate; 5 folders (Box 55)
      Typescript and manuscript. Short biographical sketches of F.W. Dawson, I, memoirs, memorandums written by Dawson regarding the true circumstances surrounding his father's murder.
    - Dawson, Warrington. Yorktown Sesquicentennial Association Bulletins, 1921-1931 (Box 55)
    - Dawson, Warrington and Vance Thompson. The Lover and the Lunatic, undated (Box 60)
      Manuscript and typescript. Includes typewritten advertisement for the two short stories.
    - Dawson, Warrington and Jean Weelen. Rochambeau: A French Soldier in the War for American Independence, undated; 6 folders (Box 60)
      Typescript. 2 copies.
    - Miscellaneous Writings, undated; 12 folders (Box 55, 63)
      Typescript and manuscript. Unidentified fragments.
  - Writings by Others, 2
    - Barry, Herbert. Till Death Us Do Part. and The Early Years, 1931-1932 (Box 96)
      Offprints from the Virginia Law Review.
    - Burdayron, Helene Marie. [A Verse for Sarah Dawson], undated (Box 56)
      Manuscript. Presumed to be a verse written by Helene Marie Burdayron for Sarah Dawson. French. Inscription at end partially illegible.
    - Charier, Camille. L'amitie Franco-Americaine, undated (Box 56)
      Typescript. Multiple copies.
    - Colvin, Sidney. Some Personal Recollections - Robert Louis Stevenson, 1920 (Box 56)
      Typescript. From Scribner's Magazine, March 1920.
    - Conrad, Jessie. Friendship's Friend., undated (Box 56)
    - Conrad, Joseph. Introduction to Virgin of Ivory, undated (Box 56)
    - Cuthbert, J.H. The Old First Baptist Church - Charleston, S.C, undated (Box 56)
      Manuscript. Song of remembrance.
    - Guerin, M. and C. Schmitt. Projet pour la Construction d'un Theatre a Versailles, undated (Box 56)
    - Hemphill, J.C. Captain Francis Warrington Dawson, 1907 (Box 56)
      Typescript. Portion of a biographical article.
    - [The Ladies' Club]. Lecture Poster, undated (Box 64)
      Hand-drawn broadside. Poster for lecture by Warrington Dawson on Joseph Conrad hosted by The Ladies' Club.
    - Ladoux, Georges. The Kaiser's Blond Spy, undated; 2 folders (Box 56)
      Typescript. Page proofs with edits. Preface and edits by Warrington Dawson. Accompanied by a folder of photographs of Mata Hari and Elsbeth Schragmüller.
    - Ladoux, Georges. Marthe Richard: The Skylark, undated; 2 folders (Box 56)
      Typescript. Page proofs and press extract. Edited with a biographical introduction and notes by Warrington Dawson. Includes photograph of Marthe Richard.
    - Ladoux, Georges. Mere D'Espionne, undated (Box 56)
    - Larrabee, Harold A. [Writings], 1929-1934 (Box 96)
      A number of articles and offprints given to Warrington Dawson by Harold Larrabee, some with personal notes from Larrabee. Titles include "Un Chapitre Peu Connu de la Vie D'Henri de Saint-Simon," "Herman Melville's Early Years in Albany," "The Jameses: Financier, Heretic, Philosopher," and "A Neglected French Collaborator in the Victory of Yorktown: Claude-Anne Marquis de Saint-Simon."
    - Morgan, George W. [Manuscript], undated; 2 folders (Box 56)
      Manuscript and typescript. Both copies of the original. Typescript accompanied by note from Warrington Dawson detailing how he acquired the text.
    - Morgan, James Morris. Colonel George Morgan: "A Forgotten Pioneer", undated (Box 56)
      Typescript. "Compiled from letters in the archives of the State Department - and letters, manuscripts, and original memorandum in the possession of his descendants."
    - Morgan, James Morris. [Essays on the Morgan Family], undated (Box 56)
      Typescript and manuscript. Various essays on the Morgan family, including John and George Morgan.
    - Morgan, James Morris. A Forgotten Man, undated (Box 56)
      Manuscript and typescript. Accompanied by note from Dawson detailing the provenance and familial relations.
    - New York Herald. US May Mediate Eventually, 1914 Sep 10 (Box 56)
      Typescript. Mentions conversation with William Graves Sharp.
    - Pré, Lucille de. Sonnet of Courage. The Men Ordered to Fight, undated (Box 56)
      Manuscript and typescript. Includes handwritten note presumably to Warrington Dawson.
    - Rhoades, Jennie W. [August 31st, 1886] (Box 66)
      Typescript. Handwritten note from author. First lines reads: "Brilliant! for all the rainbow hues illume"
    - Robertson, James I., Jr. Foreword and footnotes to a new edition of A Confederate Girl's Diary, undated (Box 56)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore. [Cornerstone Speech], undated (Box 56)
      Typescript with edits in Roosevelt's hand. 3 copies.
    - Roosevelt, Theodore. [Nairobi Speech], undated (Box 56)
      Typescript with edits in Roosevelt's hand. Also contains handwritten note from Warrington Dawson with more information.
    - Roosevelt, Theodore. [Race Relations], undated (Box 56)
      Typescript. Extracts of letters and speeches.
    - Savelle, Max. George Morgan, Esquire, Gentleman of the American Revolution, undated (Box 56)
    - Sharp, William Graves. Souvenirs de mon Ambassade, undated; 8 folders (Box 57)
      Typescript. Translated and annotated by Warrington Dawson.
    - Sharp, William Graves. The War Memoirs of William Graves Sharp: American Ambassador to France 1914-1919, undated; 20 folders (Box 57-58)
      Typescript. Edited with notes and a biographical introduction by Warrington Dawson, Confidential Adviser to Ambassador Sharp.
    - Thayer, N. M. Assurance, undated (Box 58)
      Typescript with dedication to Sarah E. Seiwell.
    - Thompson, Vance. A Boy's Recollections of His Father, undated (Box 58)
      Typescript. Fragments.
    - Thompson, Vance. [Biographical Sketch of Warrington Dawson], undated (Box 58)
    - Thompson, Vance. [Notes on the Dawsons], undated (Box 58)
    - Weelen, Jean. Rochambeau or 'The Friend of Men', undated (Box 58)
    - [White, Charles ?] [Journal Extracts], undated (Box 58)
      Manuscript. Noted to probably be written by Charles White, the cousin of Warrington Dawson.
    - White, E.A. The Right of Comitting (sic) Suicide; Description of Arcadia; Revenge, undated (Box 58)
- Printed Material and Miscellany
  This contains various printed material and miscellaneous items, including calling cards, ephemera, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and memorabilia.
  Among bills, receipts, and legal papers are materials of J. M. Morgan and the DeSaussure-Trenholm family, financial papers of the Charleston News and Courier, and records of the settlement of the estate of Frank Dawson.
  - Calling Cards, undated; 2 folders (Box 91)
    Warrington Dawson's collection of calling cards. Many with personal notes.
  - Envelopes from Autograph Collection, undated (Box 91)
    Empty envelopes with biographical information printed on them.
  - Ephemera, 1890-1933, undated (Box 91)
    Miscellaneous printed documents.
  - Invitations, Press Passes, Menus (Box 91)
  - Wedding Invitations, Sympathy Cards, Holiday Cards (Box 91)
  - Clippings: General Joffre, 1933, undated (Box 92)
    Miscellaneous clippings pertaining to General Joffre.
  - Clippings: Theodore Roosevelt, Grace King, and Miscellaneous (Box 92)
  - Clippings: Joseph Conrad (Box 92)
  - Clippings: The Cash Case (Box 92)
  - Clippings: Vance Thompson (Box 92)
  - Pamphlets, Leaflets, and Clippings on Theodore Roosevelt (Box 92)
  - The Truth About British East Africa: Being a Speech Delivered by the Hon. Col. Theodore Roosevelt, 1909 (Box 92)
    Pamphlet and reprint.
  - Big Game Shooting in East Africa, 1909 (Box 92)
  - The Startling and Voracious History of the Sotik Punitive Force, undated (Box 92)
  - The Roosevelt Big Game Record Book, undated (Box 92)
  - League of Nations on "Traffic in Women and Children", 1921-1925 (Box 92)
    Series of pamphlets.
  - Pfälzisches Museum - Pfälzische Heimatkunde: Ein Gruß der Heimat den Pfälzern in der Fremde, 1922 (Box 92)
  - Constitution and By-Laws of the Survivors' Association (Charleston), 1869 (Box 92)
  - Waldhaus Flims, undated (Box 92)
  - Zadkiel's Almanac for 1888 (Box 92)
  - Swahili: A Vocabulary of Useful Phrases, etc., etc., 1909 (Box 92)
  - Post Office Hand-Book of Foreign Mails and General Information, 1909 (Box 92)
  - Uganda Notes: A Journal of Missionary and General Interest, 1909 (Box 92)
  - In the Supreme Court of S.C.: Appeal from Charleston County, 1887 (Box 92)
  - Papers in the Case of C.W. Buttz vs. E.W.M. Mackey, 1876 (Box 92)
  - Pamphlets Related to F.W. Dawson, I, 1869-1885, undated (Box 93)
    Various pamphlets related to F.W. Dawson, I. Includes court cases, applications to societies, and records of club meetings.
  - Miscellaneous Family Information and Research Requests (Box 93)
  - Yorktown Material (Box 93)
  - Williamsburg Material (Box 93)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, Leaflets, Pamphlets, and Articles, 5 folders (Box 93)
  - Press Clippings: Ships (Box 94)
  - Saison d'Arts Francais a Versailles, 1947 (Box 94)
  - Service de la Bibliotheque Americaine de Paris aux Francais, undated (Box 94)
    By Dr. W. Dawson Johnston.
  - The Lookout, Vol. I, No. I, undated (Box 94)
  - Menu from Captain's Dinner, 1909 (Box 94)
    Signed by the attendees, including Theodore Roosevelt. Also accompanied by handwritten note from Warrington Dawson with further details on the dinner.
  - East Africa Protectorate Gun License and Tax Documents, 1909 (Box 94)
  - Art Documentation, 1932-1933 (Box 94)
    Official documents regarding artwork owned by Warrington Dawson.
  - Programs: Miscellaneous (Box 94)
  - Scout Memorabilia, undated (Box 94)
    Includes scout pins.
  - Bills and Receipts, Warrington Dawson, 1920s-1930s (Box 94)
  - Bills and Receipts, F.W. Dawson, 1870s-1910 (Box 94)
  - Legal Documents, Warrington Dawson, 1915-1918 (Box 94)
  - Legal Documents, F.W. Dawson, 1868-1888 (Box 94)
  - Musicals and Music (Box 95)
    Various programs, announcements, and clippings.
  - The Southern Club Woman, 1929 (Box 95)
    Includes article on Sarah Morgan Dawson.
  - Works on/by Warrington Dawson (Box 95)
    Miscellaneous clippings and articles on and by Warrington Dawson.
  - The Incredible Life of Warrington Dawson, Parts I-III, 1958 (Box 95)
    Printed in the News and Courier.
  - Selections from the Poetical Works of Robert Downing (Box 95)
    Book containing Warrington Dawson's notes.
  - Charleston Murders (Box 95)
  - Financial Documents, 1882-1903 (Box 95)
  - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 95)
  - Fresh Air Art Society (Box 95)
  - Mark Twain Society Membership, Warrington Dawson, 1931 (Box 95)
  - Financial Documents, 1850-1948 (Box 95)
  - Financial Papers, 1920-1954 (Box 95)
  - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 96)
  - Hair of Sarah Morgan Dawson (Box 96)
  - Rapport des Commissaires, 1904 (Box 96)
  - In Memoriam: Francis W. Dawson by the Vanderbilt Benevolent Association, 1889 (Box 96)
  - Tribute to Capt.- Dawson from the Merchants' Exchange, of Charleston, So. Ca., undated (Box 96)
  - In Memoriam: Proceedings of the Meeting of the National Democratic Committee [...] Commemorative of the Lives and Public Service of William H. Barnum and F.W. Dawson, 1889 (Box 96)
  - Memorials to F.W. Dawson, I, 1899; 3 folders 3 folders and one scroll. (Box 96, Box 100)
    One folder of oversize memorials and one oversized scroll memorial.
  - Maps, 1750-1930, undated (Box 100)
  - Membership Papers for l'Association Syndicale de la Press Etrangere, Warrington Dawson, 1909 (Box 100)
  - Knighting Papers for F.W. Dawson, I, 1883 (Box 98)
    Housed in original container. Accompanied by photocopied typescript of original manuscript.
  - Clippings: South Carolina and Charleston Reconstruction Articles (Box 99)
  - Clippings: S.C. and Printing Frauds (Box 99)
  - Clippings: Miscellaneous Clippings, Obituaries, "The Story of South Carolina" (Box 99)
  - Cartoons from Judge (Box 99)
  - The Leader of British East Africa, 1910 Aug 6 (Box 99)
  - Lafayette Genealogy (Box 99)
  - Clippings: Charleston Earthquake, 1886 (Box 99)
  - Clippings: News and Courier (Box 99)
  - Clippings: Sarah Morgan Dawson (Box 99)
  - Clippings: Biographical Clippings on F.W. Dawson, I (Box 99)
  - Clippings: Death of F.W. Dawson, I (Box 99)
  - Clippings: Murder of F.W. Dawson, I and Trial of Dr. McDow (Box 99)
  - Gold cufflinks (Box 96)
- Miscellaneous Photographs, 2
  - Warrington Dawson's Versailles Apartment, undated (Box 84)
  - News and Courier Offices Charleston, SC, undated (Box 84)
  - Banco Portugues do Continente e Ilhas, undated (Box 84)
  - Boyscouts of America, Charleston, SC, undated (Box 84)
  - Millet Francois; Millet, Geraldine, 1903 (Box 84)
    Photograph with inscription: "With affectionate regards, Geraldine Millet. Madame S. Dawson. Barbizon le 31 aout 1903 (F. Millet)
  - Officers of the Good Ship "Sam Handford", 1898 (Box 84)
    List of officers under photograph. Includes "Sonny" Stewart Dawson.
  - First Floor Plan: Manor of Cour-de-France, undated (Box 84)
  - Sketches from Nassau, Bahamas, 1861-1864 (Box 84)
    Explanation accompanying sketches reads: "The sketchs (sic) within were made for your 'stepmother,' Virginia Fourgeaud, in Nassau during the war. Mr. Floyd, of the Florida Confederate cruiser made them, I believe. The English man is, or was after this, Lord Cooper." Virginia Fourgeaud was F.W. Dawson's first wife, who died in 1872.
  - Watercolor by F. Weber, undated (Box 84)
  - Versailles Scene, undated (Box 84)
  - Monument to French War Dead, undated (Box 84)
  - Images of Historical Figures, undated (Box 84)
    Includes portraits of: Madame de Sevigne, Edmond Waller, John Bright, Napoleon, and Louise Caroline Alberta
  - Charleston, SC, undated (Box 84)
  - Chateau de Josselin, 1910 (Box 84)
    Inscription gives date of 1910
  - Miscellaneous Photographs from Roosevelt Expedition, undated (Box 85)
  - Illustrations to Accompany Text of "Opportunity and Theodore Roosevelt", undated (Box 85)
    Includes list of illustrations.
  - Roosevelt in Africa: His hunting trip in sixteen pictures, 1910 (Box 85)
    Set of postcards in original envelope. Actually includes 17 pictures, one in duplicate.
  - French Fliers, undated (Box 85)
  - Dedication of Monument to Col. George Morgan, 1929 (Box 85)
    2 copies of photograph. One has typewritten note and other has handwritten note that give further information on event and participants.
  - Bradford, O., 1888 (Box 85)
  - Burdayron, Helene Marie, undated (Box 85)
    Dawson's French maid.
  - Chack, Paul, undated (Box 85)
    Inscription on back to Warrington Dawson.
  - Chamberlain, Daniel Henry, undated (Box 85)
  - Conrad, Jessie, undated (Box 85)
  - Conrad, Joseph, 1913, 1923, undated (Box 85)
    Includes image of Joseph Conrad at age 3. A number of the photographs are inscribed to Warrington Dawson from Conrad.
  - Joseph Conrad Family Photos, undated; 2 folders (Box 85)
    Second folder includes photographs with American novelist Ellen Glasgow.
  - Grew, Joseph Clark, 1924 (Box 85)
  - Forbes, Archibald, undated (Box 85)
  - George, Henry, 1881 (Box 85)
    Inscription on back to Captain Dawson.
  - Kelly Memorial Pictures: French Manuscripts of Remembrance, 1946-1947 (Box 85)
  - Lee, Fitzhugh, 1880 (Box 85)
  - Litvinne, Felia, 1913, undated (Box 85)
    All three cards have inscriptions.
  - McLaws, Lafayette, 1863 (Box 85)
  - Riscaldino, Pierre, 1934 (Box 85)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, undated (Box 85)
  - Ruffin, Edmund, undated (Box 85)
    Handwritten note on back: "Ruffin fired the first Gun of Fort Sumter."
  - Wilson, Woodrow, undated (Box 85)
  - Windsor-Clive, Ivor Miles, Second Earl of Plymouth, undated (Box 85)
  - Unidentified Photographs, 1933 and undated (Box 85)
  - Unidentified Photograph, 1932 (Box 86)
  - Wallace, Hugh C., 1921 (Box 86)
  - Friends of F.W. Dawson, II, who were in his musical salons., 1928-1935, undated (Box 86)
    Various signed photographs. Some with notes.
  - Dawson Home and Silver Service, undated (Box 86)